In this lecture, we're going to discuss another architectural decision or
consideration while building our rack based application and that is the vector DB.
Okay, before we look at all the options, a quick 20 second overview.
So we've previously discussed, let's say we have this long PDF documents.
So we're going to create multiple chunks, then we're going to pass it through the embedding model,
create vector embeddings, and then we're going to store it in a vector store or a vector DB.
Some of the popular ones from AWS are open search and Pine Code.
Now let's go and review what are the vector DB options available with AWS and
which one should we select for our use case.
Okay, so the first one is the Amazon Aurora Postgres with PG vector plug-in extension.
So we already know about Amazon Aurora Postgres.
It's been there for quite a while.
Now what they have done is they have added this PG vector plug-in or extension,
so it can act as a relational database plus a vector database.
So it's a relational database with vector rack.
So it's highly cost effective for smaller deployments and what's the best use case for
Amazon Aurora Postgres SQL with PG vector.
It's best for applications needing both traditional SQL capabilities and vector capabilities.
So when you need a hybrid SQL plus vector, then you use Amazon Aurora Postgres.
Now the second option is Amazon Neptune Analytics.
Okay, Neptune Analytics is a graph based vector search.
So it's ideal for connected data use cases such as social media,
think about Facebook, so you're connected to a friend who's connected to multiple friends.
So you can see there is kind of a graph network that's there.
So let's say I use case on social media or fraud analytics,
where you have a lot of interconnected nodes, then Amazon Neptune Analytics is a good option.
So use case for Neptune Analytics ideal for complex relationship based queries and knowledge
graphs. So if you're looking for a vector store that can handle complex relationship
based queries and knowledge graph like social media, fraud detection,
then this is the right vector DB for you.
Now next we have Amazon open search serverless, which is probably the most popular
vector DB that is currently being used within AWS.
So Amazon open search comes in two flavors.
It's serverless where you pay only for what you use and then you also have the provision mode
where you can provision OC use or open search compute units.
Amazon open search is great for search and analytics.
So let's say you have log analytics and monitoring.
So take the example of cloud watch logs, so that's where you can use open search.
Then it's also great for enterprise search e-commerce and product search.
So these are some of the use cases for open search.
Now it provides flexible search options, including traditional keyword search,
vector search and hybrid search. So please remember this is important.
So open search is focused on keyword search and vector search and hybrid approaches.
So open search can store and search billions of high-dimensional vectors in millisecond using
advanced algorithm. So if you want millisecond response, then you have to go with open search.
So what's a good use case for Amazon open search serverless?
So Amazon open search is strong in full tech search analytics and vector search with low latency
response. So remember that open search is not only meant for vector search, but also for
keyword search. So next we have the pine cone. So it's a purpose built vector database.
So probably only vector database, which is just meant for storing vectors.
Most of the others are hybrid. So it's optimized for high-performance similarity search.
And what are the use cases? So if you need high-performance vector search and right,
then pine cone is the service for you. Okay, then finally we have the Redis Enterprise Cloud.
So it's an in-memory data platform with vector search support. So remember in the Redis Enterprise
Cloud, we already know it's a in-memory database for cache. So in case of, so it stores the vector
embedding in memory. So it combines the vector search and caching. And as we already discussed,
it's in-memory vector search for rag workloads. Now what's the benefit of using Redis Enterprise
Cloud? So it delivers ultra low latency real-time vector similarity search.
And that's mainly because it is in-memory. So it's best suited for real-time journey applications
requiring sub-millisecond to millisecond responses. Now remember, we had also set same for open search,
but this is in-memory and open search is not an in-memory vector DB. Okay, now in summary based on
your use case, how do you make the decision for the right vector DB? So you select open search,
if your use case requires keyword search, analytics, and vectors. You select pine cone, if you need
large-scale purpose built vector DB. You select Aurora PG vector, if you need relational database,
plus vectors. And you select Redis, if you need fastest in-memory real-time vector DB. Okay,
so that's pretty much it from this lecture. I'll see in the next lecture. Thank you.